hi welcome back to gift of liberation
and this is geshe michael and i'm
excited about our course
uh it's going to be a very deep course
and we're going to continue talking
about
this like you know everybody talks about
bodhichitta
and we hear this word oh borichira and
i think you know a few people still
think it means
enlightenment mind and then they think
it means the mind of a buddha
because bodhi means buddha and chitta
means mind and of course it doesn't mean
that
what it means is the wish to reach
enlightenment
and you know if we study it for two or
three
courses alarm alarming courses and two
or three retreats
then i think we also start to forget
what is bodhichitta you can say it's the
wish for enlightenment that's okay
but i i very much prefer
uh if you have the real feeling of it
and the feeling is completely different
it's not to sit and like when you're a
kid
and you're wishing for a bicycle for
christmas it's not like that
it's not like that it's a different kind
of thing so i thought maybe
at the very beginning here we can do a
small
meditation just a few minutes and you
can do a longer one in your extra
classes
but let's just do a short meditation
on on what this body should have feel
like
and and that way we can do the whole
course
and we can remember uh where we're
trying to go
uh i i will describe uh the experience
of bodhichitta
directly and then you just follow along
and imagine it
and i don't know when i was in sports
when i played tennis in
in high school they would they would
tell us to imagine yourself
uh making these great plays and doing
these great things
and my yoga teacher told me if you can't
do a pose
then just uh go halfway into a headstand
and then imagine yourself in the
headstand
and then that that's a cause for being
able to do it so we're gonna do the same
thing
uh with bodhichitta so please get ready
and we're going to do just a little tiny
meditation you do your serious
meditations
in your extra classes
eyes are soft a little bit of a smile
hands aren't soft fingers are soft i
like to touch my thumbs
i like to put my palms on each other
sit up very straight shoulders back
i like to the strange thing about
pulling in your tummy is uh
if you exhale two times
uh it your stomach will come in
automatically
and that's just good for your for your
posture
and it's good for your health so let's
do long exhales
when you run out of breath push a little
bit more breath out and your
lower stomach will tighten and that will
support your back
okay here we go 10 long exhales
they will imagine that we're having the
direct experience about the children
and imagine your mom
comes up in your mind and it's not a
picture it's not a painting
it's not a photograph it's your real mom
it's in front of your mind and
it's nice to picture her in her health
in when you knew her or you saw photos
of her
when she was young and healthy happy
and you're just sitting together
and you're like talking to her and look
mom i know
your life has not been easy life is not
always easy
i know you have worries
wherever you are now i know you have
worries i know you have
trouble in your life
and we have that big fear of death
but i want you to know that uh i
i'm gonna take care of you and i
it's not an empty promise i i have the
power i am learning the power
to take care of you and you really don't
have to worry
so you know kids are supposed to take
care of their parents when they get
older and
i've got plans for taking care of you
i i will be a buddha a real buddha
who can go to all places all times
all worlds and
knows all things and can help you
real help for you i i i'm on a fast
strike
for that so you you don't have to worry
you know i i know it's my job
to take care of you the way you took
care of me
and you don't have to worry i
i'm on a path and it works i can see
where it's going
and i can see that i will take care of
you
ultimately
and trying to picture that day when you
have that power
to move from world to world planet to
planet
galaxy to galaxy
in countless bodies
it feels like dancing across the world
and taking care of everyone in each
world
imagine that power
you your mind has that power because
your mind is empty
you have that power you just have to
wake it up
creating a mandala perfect world perfect
universe
where no one suffers no one gets old no
one dies
you have that power you are learning
how to do it you are a buddha in
training
but don't don't ever forget where you
are going
and why we are doing these courses
make that promise to your mom
okay then you can open your eyes
take a stretch yay mom
okay so
this uh this course in the alarm room uh
and and we've been going for almost 10
years now
over 10 years and we're working our way
very i don't know for me it's a great
pleasure
uh to come back to the long room every
few months
in the in the last 10 years and for me
it's like swimming
in a in a sauna or i don't know you call
this
heated swimming pool yeah or the
ocean at some pancho hosamiga on a very
nice day
and it just feels so pleasant to to come
back
to the beach called lamrim and jump in
the water again
and get a kind of
get my motivation back and get my
courage back again
and then my life doesn't seem so
difficult and
and i can dream again about becoming a
buddha
and this book is is the oh it's got to
be the greatest
book ever written for the entire
buddhist part
and and you know if you if you can read
tibetan
it's every single word is is extremely
beautiful
uh and it makes you think that true
german opportunity was
a special very special being my
teacher's teacher
so you're of a good lineage
and we're going to continue i'm going to
review
what we did in the last long room
which was what's the cool stuff
that's going to happen to you if you can
get bodhichitta
you know if you can really reach
this motivation and this vision
okay never forget the vision i don't
even like to call it motivation
get that vision in your mind of of
traveling from planet to planet
and and jumping between planets you know
it's a lot of fun and you can do it
and don't think this is the only planet
come on go out and look at the stars
some night
you know so keep that
in mind we're going to review the last
long room we had
the subject of the last long room was
really focusing
on 10 it's called penyon jun which is
the 10 benefits
of the bodhichitta the wish for
enlightenment
and if you can reach it if you can have
that direct experience
then what's it going to feel like and
how you're going to feel okay
so we're going to go through those 10
benefits
i'm going to show some items
some pictures that give you an idea of
the
benefit and the first one we can show
now
so when we talk about the first benefit
of reaching this kind of vision of
you know jumping between planets dancing
between planets
there are ten benefits and this is a
picture of the first benefit i like to
call it uh
visiting the middle of the sun and
this is called take checking
it means you will enter the greater way
and it's like going to the middle of the
sun
why do i say middle of the sun because
it's a very intense
good karma a very very high good karma
the the good karma of imagining yourself
dancing between planets and helping
people is is
incredible just a good karma of
imagining it
is you can't even feel it right so and
when i first taught this uh you know
last summer
uh we were we were talking about the
virus and
how could we help to stop the virus and
we were talking about if we could send
the virus
to the middle of the sun then that would
be great
you know that it'd be great if we could
if we could send the virus to
be destroyed in the middle of the sun
and
uh also we in between that time
we had the medicine buddha retreat and
all of us were doing a lot of uh
dedication
helping save the life of animals uh
thinking of ways to save the environment
with our carbon offset program and
different ways of helping
life on this planet for example not
eating meat
and then you know people started to
write me
oh things are happening you know this
karma's working
you know and i think i don't know about
you guys but in america
we are very uh what do you call that we
don't believe those things you know
we are very skeptical we're like ah come
on don't be superstitious you know
yeah we studied the medicine buddha yeah
we meditated on on saving life
and yeah we made plans to to stop
pollution and save the forest and
but come on you know it's not really
going to change things like that but
suddenly
i don't know about you but i started
noticing things happening
uh the vaccination came out the
vaccination was finished
uh i i don't know they used to take 10
years 20 years to develop a vaccination
and this one was developed in in less
than a year
and then they started giving it and i i
actually didn't
call anybody i didn't plan to get a
vaccination just
some friends call me oh go there they're
going to give you a vaccination you know
so i went there and
i got my vaccination veronica got a
vaccination jigme got a vaccination
first and second one and now suddenly
you know
today i was yesterday we went to a
restaurant for the first time
and we had such a good time uh
not wearing a mask you know it was so
pleasant and uh
it suddenly started things started
happening you know mcdonald's
announced uh you know i was looking for
a recipe to cook something at home
because veronica's a very good cook and
get you michael's okay cook but not like
veronica
and i thought oh i want to learn some
new recipes
and i was looking for vegetarian food
and and i found a
an advertisement from mcdonald's and
they are making
uh vegetarian meat
plant-based meat you know and uh it's a
big big thing now in
in asia in singapore for example you can
get your chicken mcnuggets are made from
plants
and this guy was so cute he said
okay i'm gonna cook some i bought some
uh uncooked
we're gonna cook them together and i was
watching the cook's video
and he cooked this non-meat
chicken and then he showed how to cook
it and then he
dried it and then he tried one he was
like
oh my god that tastes so good you know
and i was like yeah you know and
mcdonald's announced they're gonna
serve in mcdonald's and i was so happy
then bill gates
one of the wealthiest guys in the world
he finished a book
and his suggestion in the book is that
all
wealthy countries oecd uh
should become plant-based meat all of
them and it would save the environment
you know
and he had a very great chapter about
that and then i got an email from
starbucks they say
come in on monday it's a meatless monday
you know starbucks is not serving meat
on monday
and you can have lots of tasty things
vegetarian things and i thought oh my
god
when mcdonald's and starbucks
changed to vegetarian it means
my comments are working it means this
lamrim body cheddar meditation
is definitely working okay so i don't
think it's superstitious
i think it's real and i want you to
encourage you
to think that we created that
okay those lamrim guys and those
medicine buddha guys
we changed mcdonald's we made
the meat industry vegetarian we made
vegetarian meat you know
that's so cool and i want to encourage
you
to believe in it okay like don't be so
skeptical
and don't be mean you know don't say ah
that's
superstition it's not superstition okay
i believe
uh assalamu guys and that's medicine
buddha guys
we changed uh starbucks and we changed
mcdonald's and we changed bill gates uh
with our with our alarm rim so
congratulations
when you get to tantra when you get to
the diamond way
it's a bad deed not to believe that you
can change something
it's a bad deed to think you didn't
change mcdonald's so
let's celebrate okay we changed
mcdonald's congratulations
you know mcdonald's started in phoenix
arizona
my the first mcdonald's was uh next to
my
to the library my mom used to take us
there and she would buy us
french fries and uh you know that was
about
50 60 years ago and unbelievable
you know i never thought that i would
see a mcdonald's
hamburger it's not a hamburger okay
congratulations you guys
all right second uh advantage and here
we are reviewing
uh the last normium so my idea for this
first class together
is we're just going to review uh the 10
benefits of bodhichitta the first
benefit
is you know you get this incredible
karma
that can change anything okay we can say
uh in tibetan it's called
take changi jugo semke it's the only way
to get into the into the mahayana
so forget mahayana as a philosophy from
ancient india don't think like that
mahayana means jumping from planet to
planet and
and you got there okay you are there
okay all right second one let's look at
the tibetan
tim uh you're ready
yeah okay
uh means uh daughter
or son of the buddha ming toppa means
you get that name
you get the name and it's such a sexy
name i
i think there was a rock and roll song
when i was younger called bodhisattva
and i didn't know what to body stuff at
that time but
it sounded so nice to me the word
sounded so nice to me
and the song got very popular
and you you will get the name
bodhisattva it's like tim you're getting
a degree
in the college you know they're giving
you a
a degree it's like okay that's a buddha
on the left
and you and me are on the right and uh
buddha's like okay this is your degree
you know now you have a new name like
doctor tim
or i don't know pao and pachi
pao pachi phd and uh
but now they're gonna call you
barisafatu
or a bodhisattva bodhisattva girl's name
okay and you get a new name
and you get a new degree and it's
it's really really beautiful it's so
beautiful
to know that you're a bodhisattva and
when you hear people say bodhisattva
you know i think bodhisattvas usually
don't tell people they're very selfless
but
when you hear people say bodhisattva
you're like
yeah that's me they're talking about me
you know
and you feel happy you just feel really
happy oh yeah
i got that name i have that degree but
yourself a degree okay
that's the second benefit okay third
benefit
and this is a very very famous
uh and much much described in the
commentaries okay
means a listener and
nyan means listener and rang means
rang-san gay means self-made buddha
but the point is that these are very
very
deep spiritual practitioners
who don't have that vision they don't
have that vision
of going from planet to planet but they
are
very beautiful people their meditation
is really great
their morality is perfect their
concentration is perfect
everything about them is is really
amazing and i i like this picture
of uh i have this idea of an ocean
i saw this picture and it reminded me of
this idea
that uh the birds in the picture
are like arhats okay they reach nirvana
these birds
are to me i like to think they are
listeners
and self-made buddhas and it's beautiful
to watch them
especially at sunset over the ocean
but the sun okay but the sun
okay you can see the reflection of the
sun you cannot see the sun
but compared to the sun the beauty of
the birds is
it's beautiful but it's nothing compared
to the sun the whole sun
lighting up the whole world compared to
those birds the birds are beautiful they
are
arhats they reach nirvana they are
listeners they are self-made buddhas
they are people who didn't have that
vision
bodhisattva vision and then the sun
is that higher vision and you become
like the sun when you when you're a
bodhisattva
and you have that higher vision you
become like the sun
it doesn't mean the birds aren't
beautiful they are beautiful
in fact the sun makes them more
beautiful but
imagine if you could be the birds and
the sun okay something like that
all right uh fourth benefit
is called chubby chin choctage okay
means to make offerings xing means
garden in this case garden and
choctagirwa
means you become the highest one
you become the highest garden
where people can plant the good of good
karma
of offering and i imagine you know
wouldn't it be cool if you're really a
bodhisattva
and you walk into the coffee shop
and you order a coffee okay like you
just
walk into the car we have a coffee shop
next to college i'm thinking that like
this lady just became bodhisattva she
had that vision nobody knows she's a
body stopper
but she did reach that vision
in her meditation directly she saw the
real thing
and now this guy is offering her a
coffee and
listen that guy offering her the coffee
he suddenly makes this intense good
karma
he suddenly gets this incredible
good karma because he's serving your
coffee
and your buddy sapa okay so everyone who
everyone who is sweet to a bodhisattva
is collecting extraordinary karma and
wouldn't it be nice
to be the bodhisattva okay every time
someone comes close to you
and smiles at you or helps you in any
way
and they don't even know their karma's
like a million times
more they don't even know about it okay
but you are making other people happy
just by drinking their coffee at their
coffee shop that's so cool
all right uh fifth benefit
okay so here means uh some of you heard
the word sulk
for a dharma party and it means uh lots
of good things to
eat and lots of good things to drink
that's called it so
a lot lots of cool offerings gaucho
means very big
and de la zopa means you can make good
karma
very very quickly and i was trying to
think of a photograph for this and
gail said do you remember it when we
first started diamond mountain
uh university we the retreat center
then uh we were thinking to build roads
so we could connect retreat cabins
and and so i don't know 100 people
went out in the desert and
we picked up rocks it was so funny 100
people
walked about 50 steps in two hours and
we just pick up a rock
and we throw them on the sun you know
and we are making a road you know
and it was so funny and we worked so
hard oh my god
you know you guys go to diamond mountain
retreat center now you're so lucky
uh people work so hard and and i
remember we
said let's build a room and we used to
do that in boy scouts
let's build a road we would work for
like five days
and build a road for like 100 yards
and uh so then we all sewing rocks you
know
then later we got more money we got more
support and
here's the picture uh
yeah this is the these machines came to
diamond mountain this is diamond
mountain
uh these are the machines that were paid
for by our sponsors and
and i it's difficult uh i took this
picture
but um the wheel of the machine
is bigger than me it's taller than me
you know
uh and you can make a road i don't know
in a few hours
uh you can push those big rocks to the
side
and bodhichitta you know this
bodhisattvas
heart the buddhist office mind is like
those big machines
okay you want to make good karma then
stop
uh it's good karma to pick up rocks at
time mom
but it's going to take your 100 years to
build a road you know
go get one of those stupid machines you
know
bigger the tires bigger than me taller
than me
and and just use it for a couple hours
and finish the roads
the karma of being a bodhisattva is like
that okay
very very powerful very efficient okay
benefit number six
[Music]
okay and that means dig deep means uh
obstacles so we all did bad things
uh in our life we still remember uh
we're still doing them we can't stop
ourselves
sometimes we do bad things we hurt
people we do things we're not supposed
to do
and then immediately it creates an
obstacle in our life
and we've been doing that for our whole
life many years
and collecting obstacles one by one we
can
remove them just by having that
bodhisattva's vision
okay so let's call bodhichitta
the vision of a bodhisattva just by
imagining
going from planet to planet helping
people
just thinking about it can remove all
these obstacles you have in your
business life
in your health in your relationships
in your state of mind just
imagining once in a while
this goal of dancing from planet to
planet
is enough to remove all those obstacles
you can take medicines you can go to
doctors
you know you can go to marriage
counselors
you can talk to business consultants
for many years
and you you won't remove the obstacles
like you can
with a few short body chitter
meditations
okay it's just very cool it's very
efficient
save a lot of money also okay all right
uh benefit number seven
uh chi samba dupa cheese samba dupa
means
cheese sampa means whatever you want
anything you can think of cheese sample
is a nice word
it means anything you can think of dupa
you can get it okay
anything you can think of and i love
this organic
way to get things in your life you know
i i don't worry about money
and it was never my goal in my life to
be wealthy if i thought if i tried i
could be
but i it's not some it's not my priority
it's not
something i want but i would like to
have a lot of money it would be fun
you know i could do so many good things
mr ben in vietnam
he just built 400 houses for poor people
i think that's so cool you know i would
like to have money like that
and i would like to have a perfect uh
relationship
at home with with my wife i i'd like
that to be
and i'd like to be healthy i don't want
to be sick you know those things i want
those are things i want and the amazing
thing is
just this bodhisattva opinion just
thinking about it once in a while
things start to happen in your life the
karma is so intense
that cool stuff starts to happen in your
life and
you start to build this perfect world
without thinking about it you know
you're not like oh i want to get rich or
you're not like
oh i want to be super healthy but
suddenly all these things are happening
to you
if you keep coming back to this vision
you got a picture for me
apache city in the sun yeah
yeah i'm thinking this is a picture like
shenzhen
and uh you know
in a way this this is a beautiful
combination i love this city
in china because they mix
these beautiful buildings with nature
and
and as you walk through the city there's
a beautiful balance
you know people need homes to stay in
people need offices
so there are these beautiful buildings
and
and there's a sensitivity to the
environment and
there's a nice mixture of in in that
particular city
of nature and without thinking
without planning if you just come back
to this vision
a few times a day the karma is so
intense
that you will start to have beauty
and and physical wealth around you
that you didn't dream of in beautiful
relationships and
things you didn't dream of okay all
right uh
number eight benefit number eight 8
[Music]
means things that would cause you
trouble uh
parche means means
interruption and you know my teacher
used to get really irritated if he was
meditating
and someone would knock on the door or
something that's called party parche
means
your meditation's going really good and
then somebody knocks on the door that's
called parche so
if you have this vision of
bodhisattva's vision then those apaches
okay uh you'll be protected i like the
picture
patchy really
okay and look i know it's a military
thing i know it's not
it's not a nice thing it's true it's a
it's a very bad thing
but you know wind tanks
still in this world
country's power is calculated
by the number of tanks okay still they
say
this country has four hundred and four
thousand
this country has three thousand this
country has hundred thousand tanks
and if you can imagine a war
and if you imagine bullets flying here
and there and people getting killed
every every every few yards every few
meters somebody's dying
you know then there's this guy relaxing
in the tank you know
probably he's having a cappuccino again
and
there's bullets and bombs and you know
people dying and he's just relaxing in
the tank you know
because nothing can get through the tank
you know and i know
in the movies they like to show brad
pitt goes out and
and hits the tank with his hand and it
breaks down and it's not like that in a
real war you know the tank comes through
and
kills everybody and the guys in the tank
are just relaxing you know
and you can't touch them so bodhichitta
is like sitting in a tank okay and the
whole world can be crazy
and insane people can be doing terrible
things to each other
and you're just in this bubble uh
of buddhist protection you know just
things
things don't happen to you like they
happen to other people disasters
problems you know all kinds of
disturbances in their life happen to and
and even you feel guilty oh i'm in the
body to the bubble
and other people are not and oh look
they're having so much trouble
yesterday a friend of mine her brother
committed suicide
and and i have to see this i have to
meet her i have to talk to her you know
and
[Music]
i feel like oh just get in the bubble
you know just get in the tank
you know just think about bodhichitta
once in a while and
you won't have this you can be protected
okay
that's the eighth benefit okay ninth
benefit
salaam tam jinyu okay salam
salan means uh
bodhisattva levels and la means past
tamji near the zopa means quickly
you will go through all those paths so
the
spiritual progress is judged
by five paths and ten bodhisattva levels
it's very hard to get to the first one
okay it's very hard to get to the first
bodhisattva level when you get to the
first bodhisattva level
you already saw emptiness directly
that's number one
imagine what is number ten okay but if
you have bodhichitta
uh it's like you're climbing a mountain
and you're just at the top you know
right away you're at the top you know no
trouble no work
you don't feel tired just suddenly
that bodhichitta can take you to the top
okay without much trouble without much
sweat
without much trouble work hard work
if you just practice that vision we
talked about the beginning
then it's automatic you know you go to
the top of the
ten bodhisattva levels okay last benefit
joy daiki
i have a friend here in sedona her name
is they call her dicky
but her real name is dekey okay dead kid
here it is
uh dekey means super happy okay
super happy and i'll show a picture
uh this is the valley
uh and you know
this whole valley i imagine there was a
river going through there
and the whole valley is covered with
nice
uh beautiful soil
fertile soil you know you
you put seeds there it grows you know
there's places like that right
not arizona okay but there are places
where
the soil is so good that
just everything will grow there you know
automatically without any work at all
things will grow there you know
oftentimes it's river soil
the tenth benefit of the vision of the
bodhisattva
is that you become like a valley
of fertile soil for other people okay
you become like uh
people can plant their crops in you what
crops
their happiness okay you are like the
good soil and just by being around other
people
their good karma increases and they can
plant
their happiness in you with you you're
available
you're nearby and and
they you give them a chance somebody
says good morning to a buddy stuff but
they're like already gonna be in nirvana
within i don't know 10 years or
something
it's crazy okay so uh
it's nice to be the soil
that other people can use to grow the
crops
that they need to live and to be happy
it's nice to be
the person in the room that
is a very fertile soil for the happiness
of other people and needless to say when
you become a buddha
after you go through buddhism with
buddha bodhichitta motivation
you become a buddha then obviously
it's just cool to be the person who
makes billions of other people happy
okay in in the end we are not selfish
human beings are not selfish
we want to make other people happy it
makes us
happy when we make other people happy
and we know that we feel that
and a buddhist office is going to be the
one
who makes everybody else happy and just
imagine
you know you're able to throw a party
for the whole billions of people
because you have this bodhichitta okay
so that's a review of the last lumbrian
course that we had and that was just a
short review
of what we went through in the last
normal course now we're going to start
uh the actual instructions
for how to get to this vision there's
actually
seven steps easy steps we can take
and that's going to be the new alarming
course that we're starting on now let's
learn
the seven steps we can all do
to get to this vision okay so i'll see
you in the next episode